<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A gentlewoman and a scholar? on Monica Thieu</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in A gentlewoman and a scholar? on Monica Thieu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to prepare and teach an R lesson</title>
      <link>/posts/2020-08-15-prepare-teach-r-lesson/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2020-08-15-prepare-teach-r-lesson/</guid>
      <description>1 Notes for readers 2 Why this talk? 3 Objectives 4 Lesson construction using backward design  4.1 What is backward design? 4.2 Define outcomes 4.3 Define evidence of learning  4.3.1 Formative assessment: more smaller tests 4.3.2 Tidy formative assessments 4.3.3 Multiple choice check-ins scale pretty well  4.4 Build lesson  5 Deliver the lesson 6 In summary   1 Notes for readers This blog post contains a written version of my speaker notes for my 20-minute 2020 NYC R conference talk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up this website</title>
      <link>/posts/2020-08-10-setting-up-this-website/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2020-08-10-setting-up-this-website/</guid>
      <description>Setting up a blogdown repository Blogdown-ing with a different Hugo theme  Making a new homepage template  Understanding Hugo’s expected structure  Adding pages to the menu bar  Hooking it into the interwebs  Setting public as the GitHub Pages root directory Re-pointing my old Squarespace domain name  Pointing Squarespace DNS to GitHub Pages URL Get GitHub Pages URL to use new domain   Adding a photo gallery into the theme Fixing code syntax highlighting  Prism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wrangling multilevel data in the tidyverse</title>
      <link>/posts/2020-04-08-tidy-multilevel/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2020-04-08-tidy-multilevel/</guid>
      <description>1 Learning goals 2 Notes for instructors 3 Lesson body  3.1 A brief intro to multilevel structure: It’s everywhere! 3.2 Introducing the data 3.3 Reading in the data 3.4 Inspecting the data  3.4.1 Quick graphs 3.4.2 Basic summary statistics  3.5 Nesting the data  3.5.1 Intro to nest(), unnest(), and tibble list-columns  3.6 Going vectorize crazy  3.6.1 Vectorizing: it’s like a for loop, but not 3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Where I’m at. Some of my code. Talk to me. A snapshot of my CV. Awards and honors Teaching experience Publications and presentations    Where I’m at. I’m currently a PhD student in Dr. Kevin Ochsner’s Social Cognitive &amp;amp; Affective Neuroscience Lab at Columbia University, where I began in fall 2017. While I’m not working on research (and often while I am), I’m probably drinking from a very large cup of tea.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Game shows</title>
      <link>/game-shows/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/game-shows/</guid>
      <description>(2012) Jeopardy! College Championship (2013) Jeopardy! Tournament of Champions (2016) 500 Questions, season 2 (2019) Jeopardy! All-Star Games Photos (poorly organized, sorry!)   First things first…
Buy a Team Ken shirt or other swag here to represent/embarrass Ken Jennings, the GOAT. All profits donated to the Pancreatic Cancer Action Network in honor of Alex Trebek.
When I was little, instead of doing normal kid things, I would read piles upon piles of nonfiction books about history and science.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/</guid>
      <description>Research tools Recruiting online participants Running behavioral tasks online  Active projects Individual differences in age perception Measurement of emotion self-reporting  Previous projects Attention, memory, and media multitasking Healthy aging and associative memory    Research tools Recruiting online participants I recently started using prolific.co, a researcher-friendly website for online behavioral study recruitment that’s kind both to researchers and to participants. All my contacts with participants have been pleasant, and the Prolific support staff are so responsive and helpful.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>